Guide to the 90th Regiment New York Veteran Volunteer Association papers 1977.005
Brooklyn Historical Society
90th Regiment New York Veteran Volunteer Association papers
1862, 1882-1897
1884-1894
Brooklyn Historical Society
Sugden, Thomas D. (Thomas Dodgson)
1977.005
0.5 Linear Feet in one manuscript box.
The 90th Regiment New York Veteran Volunteer Association papers includes documents concerning this Civil War veterans organization, founded 1884, and to a somewhat lesser extent, Mansfield Post No. 35 of the Grand Army of the Republic (G.A.R.). These documents were written or compiled by Thomas D. Sugden, a member and sometime officer of the organizations.
Conditions Governing Access
Open to researchers without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Thomas D. Sugden, 1903.
Arrangement
Materials related primarily to the 90th Regiment Veteran Volunteer Association are arranged before those concerning Mansfield Post 35 of the G.A.R.
Historical note
The 90th Regiment New York Veteran Volunteer Association was formed in Brooklyn in 1884. Comprised of former soldiers who fought with the 90th during the Civil War, the organization aimed to support surviving veterans and perpetuate the memory of the regiment. The regiment was formed in December 1861 in New York City, and was first sent to Key West, Florida in January 1862, where many men were stricken with yellow fever. The regiment was subsequently assigned to South Carolina, New Orleans, and Virginia. It was mustered out in 1866. Thomas D. Sugden, the donor of this collection, was a member of companies I and D. He was an active member of the 90th's veteran association and held various offices. Sugden was also a member and officer of the Grand Army of the Republic (G.A.R.) Mansfield Post 35 in Brooklyn.
Related Materials
The Bennett family collection of Civil War correspondence and other material (2009.012) includes letters from a member of the 90th regiment.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes documents written or compiled by Thomas D. Sugden in connection with two Civil War veterans associations he was active in. Most of the collection concerns the 90th Regiment New York Veteran Volunteer Association. A smaller, but still significant, portion concerns Mansfield Post No. 35 of the Grand Army of the Republic (G.A.R.). Both of these organizations were based in Brooklyn, New York.
The bulk of the material dates from the 1880s and into the early 1890s. Among the documents are notes taken at meetings; ephemera such as leaflets for event announcements and admission tickets; a scrapbook of 90th Veterans Association clippings and memorabilia; Sugden's notes for his public remarks; correspondence to and from Sugden, including postcard invitations to meetings; some financial reports for Mansfield Post; and newspaper clippings. There is also a small number of admission tickets and other ephemera for other organizations' events, mostly from G.A.R. posts.
The collection includes three numbers of The New Era, which was published in Key West by editor Richard B. Locke, quartermaster of the 90th regiment. The three numbers (17, 18, and 20) date from August 1862; number 18 includes a front-page article arguing for the abolition of slavery. These three newspapers are the only items in the collection dating from the war years.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
If digital surrogates exist, they should be used in place of the originals whenever possible.
United States |x History |y Civil War, 1861-1865 |x Veterans; Veterans |z New York (State) |z Kings County |x Societies, etc.; Minutes; Admission tickets; Leaflets (printed works); Veterans |z New York (State) |x Societies, etc.; American newspapers |z Florida |z Key West; New era (Key West, Fla.); Invitations; Printed ephemera; Brooklyn (New York, N.Y.) -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865 -- Veterans; Scrapbooks; Correspondence; Clippings (information artifacts); Grand Army of the Republic. Mansfield Post No. 35 (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.); United States. Army. New York Infantry Regiment, 90th (1861-1866); 90th Regiment New York Veteran Volunteer Association (Brooklyn, New York, N.Y.)
- Correspondence, 1883-1891 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- Addresses to membership, 1889-1891 (Box 1, Folder 2)
- Meeting minutes and notes, 1884-1894 (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Meeting and event notices, 1884-1897 (Box 1, Folder 4)
- Scrapbook, 1884-1894 (Box 1, Folder 5-6)
- "The New Era" newspaper, 1862 (Box 1, Folder 7, Box OS-6)
- Clippings and publications, circa 1882-1892 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Ephemera, 1884-1897 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- Mansfield Post
  - Meeting minutes and notes, 1882-1883 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Financial records, 1883-1885 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Ephemera, 1882-1887 (Box 1, Folder 12)